<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rss.xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Bookshelf Blog</title>
        <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog</link>
        <description>The latest book reviews and thoughts.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>Copyright © 2025 My Book Shelf.</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Song of Achilles, Madeline Miller]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/songofachilles</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/songofachilles</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/1/1e/TheSongofAchilles.png" alt="Book Cover: Song of Achilles" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>An engaging retelling of Greek Mythology's greatest tales, Madeline Miller’s ‘The Song of Achilles’ will have you tearing through the pages. Based on Homer’s ‘Iliad’, this novel tells the story of the Trojan War from an entirely new perspective.</p>
<p>‘The Song of Achilles’ focuses on the themes of love, war and fate through the story of demi-God Achilles and his friend, and eventually lover, Patroclus. Narrated by the banished Prince, Patroclus, the novel gives a first person perspective into the relationship of these two protagonists. Whilst the character of Achilles is generally considered to be an egocentric figure, constantly craving battle and glory, Miller uses Patroclus to paint him in a different light. Though his hubristic nature is still prevalent, through Patroclus, we see a vulnerability previously unimagined. In turn, Miller’s depiction of this well known story is passionate and consistently evokes pathos from the reader.</p>
<p>This is by far my shortest review as I was eager to write something about it but my lack of knowledge of Greek Mythology makes it a bit harder. Don’t be put off by this as I still loved this story! Be warned… you will definitely need tissues for the inevitable tragic ending.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Fiction</category>
            <category>Greek Mythology</category>
            <category>Classics</category>
            <category>Romance</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Remains of the Day, Kazuo Ishiguro]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/remainsoftheday</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/remainsoftheday</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71+HFMIHZeL.jpg" alt="Book Cover: The Remains of the Day" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>I do not like writing reviews about books I have not enjoyed, however, I have been told recently that not all my reviews can have five star ratings! Therefore, I have decided to write about a book I read at the beginning of this summer that I was largely disappointed by.</p>
<p>Now, my opinion may be unpopular as, having read some other reviews of the book, the general consensus is that it is a touching story full of emotion and intrigue. A classic. But unfortunately, I just did not enjoy it.I believe it was lacking in plot and rather disinteresting. One of my absolute favourite books is written by Kazuo Ishiguro, ‘Never Let Me Go’, and I read ‘The Remains of the Day’ in the hope that I would be left wishing to turn back the pages as I was with Ishiguro’s other novel.</p>
<p>That being said, it was not so bad to the point where I did not wish to put it down and start another book. I truly wished to understand it, and, having finished it I can see why it is a highly regarded novel. The protagonist, a 1950s butler named Mr Stevens, has spent his life maintaining order and serving his employer to the best of his ability. Yet this all changed with the arrival of Miss Kenton, the new housekeeper. As the book progresses, Mr Stevens’ unacknowledged love for Miss Kenton becomes apparent as the story delves into one of its most central themes: regret. Alongside Stevens’ regret for not sharing how he felt about Miss Kenton in his past, the reader also sees the protagonist’s regret at misplaced loyalty as the true nature of his beloved employer surfaces.</p>
<p>Moreover, Ishiguro’s moments of comedy should not be overlooked. One motif that particularly stood out to me was Stevens’ inability to decipher banter nor engage with it himself. There is an excellent passage in which Stevens reflects on how his inability to joke with the new owner of Darlington Hall will, in his eyes, have negative consequences on his competence as a butler. This did lead me to question whether Stevens’ lack of understanding of social cues, love of planning and order and his fixation on being the best butler he can be perhaps allude to autistic characteristics. Who knows?</p>
<p>So, whilst I am not itching to read this particular novel again, there were aspects I thoroughly enjoyed and I can see why it receives, mostly, brilliant reviews. Let me know what you think!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Atmosphere, Taylor Jenkins-Reid]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/atmosphere</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/atmosphere</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81IaWUZgZaL._UF1000,1000_QL80_.jpg" alt="Book Cover: Atmosphere" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>Taylor Jenkins-Reid’s ‘Atmosphere’ is the perfect beach read. Like many of her other novels, Jenkins-Reid crafts an epic love story within an exciting, often dangerous, setting. ‘Atmosphere’ is no exception.</p>
<p>The opening chapter immerses the reader into the world of NASA, as two characters, Vanessa and Griff, embark on a space walk before disaster strikes. Meanwhile, the protagonist, astrophysicist Joan, tries to bring the team home safely back down to earth.
If this is not enough to hook you, Jenkins-Reid brings the novel back seven years ago when the team, whom you will soon know and love, first meet. Flicking between Vanessa’s and Joan’s gradual love story and the climactic moments of the team in space, Jenkins-Reid creates an original, heart-breaking love story that is not one to miss. Jenkins-Reid’s characters are, for the most part, complex, intriguing and well-developed. However, I would argue that she fails to develop some of the side characters, using them more as plot devices than characters in their own rights. Whilst this is typically okay, it may have been nice to see how others are affected by their experiences at NASA rather than just seeing them on surface level.</p>
<p>Furthermore, after having recently read Samantha Harvey’s ‘Orbital’, a beautiful novella that demands reflection from its reader, I was disappointed by Jenkins-Reid’s descriptions of space. Whilst it was clear that she had done her research around constellations and their origins, I believe she failed to grasp the true beauty and vastness of the, well, atmosphere! This opinion, however, may be slightly biased as I was unable not to compare these two novels. Therefore, since I would happily read any of Jenkins-Reid’s novels whilst lying peacefully on the beach, I will give her latest novel 3.5 stars.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Fiction</category>
            <category>Romance</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Purple Hibiscus, Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/purplehibiscus</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/purplehibiscus</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81ALbp43EtL._UF1000,1000_QL80_.jpg" alt="Book Cover: Purple Hibiscus" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie's ‘Purple Hibiscus’ is a powerful story of a young Nigerian girl raised in a wealthy, yet abusive Catholic household. Set roughly twenty years after Nigeria gained independence from British colonialism in 1960, Adichie explores the effects of colonialism, civil war and a shift in religious beliefs within a single family. She depicts the family’s struggle for a modern identity against the backdrop of a devastating military coup.</p>
<p>The novel’s narrator, Kambili Achike, is the fifteen year old daughter of the wealthy factory owner and devout Catholic, Eugene Achike. Adichie uses their relationship to demonstrate the mental manipulation of domestic abuse. For example, in Chapter One, Kambili describes the ‘love-sips’ her father would offer her and her brother, Jaja, when he drinks his tea. The scolding tea consequently becomes a symbol, in Kambili’s eyes, of Papa’s love for his children. Moreover, it acts as a symbol for Eugene’s abusive nature. Eugene and the tea are both supposed to be ‘good’ for Kambili, even if they hurt her physically. Metaphorically, it is also reflective of their relationship as, despite being harmed, Kambili idolises her father and continues to seek his love and approval. However, as the book progresses, Kambili is shown other, happier ways of living, previously unknown to her, as she and Jaja go to stay with Aunty Ifeoma. Ifeoma and her children show Jaja and Kambili the joys of family, laughter and mental freedom. Whilst Kambili is still tied by her father, she begins to feel more independent and rebellious. This arguably acts as a narrative catalyst for the subsequent events of the novel.</p>
<p>The novel also focuses on religion and how, when interpreted incorrectly, can be the cause for abuse and control. Throughout the novel, Adichie highlights how Papa believes the harm he inflicts on his family is for their own good. He persistently asks his children why they sin as if he believes he has no other choice but to punish them. Papa’s beliefs are molded by Catholic missionaries and are incredibly strict. In this way, Adichie demonstrates one of many effects of colonialism in that Papa’s religious beliefs have been Westernised yet his interpretation of the Bible is too strict and literal.</p>
<p>Finally, one of Adichie’s most impactful arguments is perhaps her insistence that Nigeria is in need of a chance to rule itself. In Chapter Seventeen, Adichie uses the character of Aunty Ifeoma to describe how ‘there are people [...] who think that [Nigeria] cannot rule [itself] because the few times we tried, we failed’. She states that it is ‘like telling a crawling baby who tries to walk, and then falls back on his buttocks, to stay there. As if the adults walking past him did not all crawl, once’. Ifeoma’s statement broadens the novel from a previously personal perspective to a reflection of the international Western military and economic control. Where the reader has seen characters throughout the novel fight for their cognitive autonomy, here, Adichie urges Nigeria and other African countries to do the same. She uses this metaphor to effectively convey the illogic of the Western belief that Nigeria cannot rule itself. In this way, there is an underlying sense of optimism to the novel’s ending despite its otherwise melancholic tone. Whilst I would argue that ‘Purple Hibiscus’ does not have a conventionally ‘happy ending’, beneath the surface Adichie does offer a sense of hope and new beginnings. However, this is just one reader’s opinion! I encourage you to read this novel and decide for yourself.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Fiction</category>
            <category>Religion</category>
            <category>Historical Fiction</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Twelfth Night, William Shakespeare]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/twelfthnight</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/twelfthnight</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://oxford-playhouse.transforms.svdcdn.com/production/Tickets-Oxford/TO-Twelfth-Night-OTG-Jul-25.jpg?w=760&amp;h=535&amp;q=100&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;dm=1743591287&amp;s=433849d0c7e39e2da72f35e5cd003d26" alt="War Horse" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>To see the Oxford Theatre Guild’s ‘Twelfth Night’, is to be transported to a place of drunken madness, lovesick folly and hilarious schemes. Directed by Michael Corbridge and Martha Gray, this modern twist on one of Shakespeare’s classics is not one to miss.</p>
<p>The very setting of OTG’s fantastic adaptation serves to immerse the audience into an evening of love, laughter and disguise. With live music and a soundtrack from the 1980’s, the play is modernised yet still in keeping with Shakespeare’s original. Having often wondered whether adding modern relevance to Shakespeare’s literary works allows their original aim to be maintained, I was pleased to see how OTG incorporated contemporary humour without disrupting the play’s essence.</p>
<p>Whilst one would expect to be brought to laughter in the presence of the humorous Sir Andrew, Sir Toby and Maria, Sir Andrew’s pink socks (and eventual pink boxing gloves) comedically emphasises the ridiculousness of some of Shakespeare’s most loved characters. A stand out performance, however, would be that of Freyja Madsen as the hilarious Malvolio who undergoes a dramatic transformation from a stiff embodiment of propriety to a ridiculous, almost pitiful personification of the power of self-delusion. OTG’s costume choice takes the already iconic cross-gartered yellow stockings to a whole new level by creating a yellow corset to match!</p>
<p>As for the play’s bemusing love triangle, typical to Shakespeare’s comedies, Ellie Higginbotham as the disguised Viola, Fifi Homan as the beautiful Olivia and Ariel Levine as the love-sick Duke Orsino remain at the center of the play’s journey of love and mistaken identity. As the character of Viola puts it, only ‘time’ can ‘untangle’ the complex series of events leading to the play’s satisfying ending. We see this with the arrival of Viola’s twin brother, Sebastian, played by the talented young actor, Joe Lamb. The dramatic irony in the final scenes, as Sebastian is comically attacked by Sir Andrew and Viola appears to be suddenly married to Olivia, is heightened by the actors’ brilliant facial expressions and consistently misguided actions.</p>
<p>‘Twelfth Night’ by the Oxford Theatre Guild is therefore not an evening to miss. Running from now until the 26th of July, there is still time for you to buy tickets and be immersed in ‘this very midsummer madness’.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ticketsoxford.com/events/twelfth-night-by-william-shakespeare" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.ticketsoxford.com/events/twelfth-night-by-william-shakespeare</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Classics</category>
            <category>Theatre</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Shuggie Bain, Douglas Stuart]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/shuggie</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/shuggie</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/71wfg-FbHiL._SY466_.jpg" alt="Book Cover: Shuggie Bain" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>Douglas Stuart’s ‘Shuggie Bain’ follows the childhood of a young boy, Shuggie, and the struggles he faced growing up in a working class background of 1980s Scotland. Despite his desperate attempts to fit in and behave like a ‘real boy’, his homosexuality is apparent leading to bullying and his own insecurity. His mother, Agnes, is an alcoholic, abandoned by almost everyone in her life, from her husband to her eldest children. Yet, Shuggie withstands her temperamental personality and unreliable mothering attributes, despite his own happiness and security. It is a story of loss, hardship and the acceptance of one’s identity. It is a story of a young boy that is forced to grow up too quickly.</p>
<p>This was perhaps one of the most perceptive portrayals of alcoholism I have ever seen in literature. Throughout the novel, Stuart evokes both sympathy and anger from the reader towards the despairing state of Shuggie’s life. The reader may hold their breath in hope that Agnes’ situation will improve whilst constantly knowing that her life is ultimately hopeless. Stuart conveys the relentless ups and downs as Agnes fights for sobriety and as Shuggie watches helplessly. Whilst the novel is primarily aimed at those who can relate to the characters, particularly in terms of the key themes of addiction, poverty and sexuality, the book is still relevant to anyone willing to widen their breadth of reading and understand the hardships faced by many. The novel is, in part, autobiographical, and I think that really comes across in the insightful portrayal of 1980s poverty. It is beautifully written and carefully captures the essence of one individual’s life.</p>
<p>One of my favourite moments was the protagonist’s description of his mother and how ‘when her belly was empty and her weans were hungry, she did her hair and let the world think otherwise’. This is one of the few examples in the novel where Agnes did right by Shuggie. I think the admiring tone created conveys the idea that it only takes small, infrequent positive moments to reinforce one's love for their family. It is also a reminder to any reader to take pride in oneself and keep their head held high. In a way, this small moment of support has an undertone of melancholy as Shuggie sees his mother’s love for him but knows that once she begins to drift into a drunken state, she will no longer be her proud self.</p>
<p>I would easily recommend this book and therefore give it four stars. I cannot wait to read Stuart’s most recent book ‘Young Mungo’.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Fiction</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[War Horse, National Theatre]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/warhorse</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/warhorse</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://greatleapforward.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/11/2019/01/War-Horse.jpg" alt="War Horse" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>On the 11th of June 2025, I saw the National Theatre’s ‘War Horse’ for the second time. Adapted for the stage by Nick Strafford, ‘War Horse’ is a compelling story of a boy’s love for his horse set against the devastating backdrop of World War One.</p>
<p>What makes ‘War Horse’ a play unlike any other, is their spectacular use of puppetry. Designed by the Handspring Puppet Company, Joey and Topthorn, the leading horses, come alive on stage. This is, in large, due to the incredible actors in control of the puppets. Each horse is controlled by a group of three actors who work together to create the horse’s character. The detail and concentration that goes into controlling these horses is unimaginable. From the changes in breath to the subtle stamp of a hoof or flick of a tail, the horses become alive in every way. I frequently had to remind myself that they were not real horses! Another way in which the puppets become alive is through the actors' interactions with them, both puppeteers and characters. By simply looking at the puppet, the actor commandeering the head of the horse drew the audience’s attention to the horses encouraging them to focus on the animal rather than the actor. Furthermore, the character’s interactions with the horses evoke a range of emotions from the audience depending on their relationship with the horse. Consequently, ‘War Horse’ is an original, immersive experience that I would see time and time again.</p>
<p>The fixed set of ‘War Horse’ consists of a projection screen designed to look like a torn piece of parchment. Throughout the play, this screen is used to project both heart-warming and heart-breaking images. For instance, when the audience sees Albert’s and Joey’s relationship begin to flourish, time is made prominent through the sketches of the passing seasons. This alongside the singer’s incredible voice and the emotive music creates a beautiful, aesthetically appealing scene. Another use of projection that stood out to me was a moment in which blood turned into poppies after the death of many of Albert’s squad in Act Two. This imaginative reminder of those lost to the war brought tears to the eyes of all those watching.</p>
<p>Undeniably, the show would not be what it is without the incredible backstage crew. Having been lucky enough to gain insight to what goes on backstage, I was made aware of the fast-paced, precise happenings that ensure each performance is at its best. The process of props being taken from and handed to the actors at the moments required was methodical and rapid. Watching the play from beneath the stage with the follow-spot crew or from behind the curtains with the stage manager heightened my appreciation for the show as a whole.</p>
<p>It would not be fair to write this review without mentioning the remarkable cast. This talented group of people are what make ‘War Horse’ a magical and unique performance. They are the force that immerse the audience into the world of Albert and Joey, take us back to the early 20th century and create a truly breathtaking experience.</p>
<p>The National Theatre’s ‘War Horse’ is certainly a five star show. I cannot wait to see it again.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Classics</category>
            <category>Theatre</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Bell Jar, Sylvia Plath]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/belljar</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/belljar</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/812nGlXCWwL.jpg" alt="Book Cover: The Belljar" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>Written just months before her suicide, Plath’s ‘The Bell Jar’ tells the story of ambitious student Esther Greenwood as her dreams of becoming a poet are put on hold due to a mental health crisis. Plath’s writing is clear, impactful and full of heart wrenching experiences. Plath entwines ambition, dissociation between mind and body and womanhood to create a compelling tale of real experiences.</p>
<p>One of my favourite moments of the novel is Plath’s description of the fig tree. Arguably, she uses this as a metaphor for the abundance of choices people can experience in life and how this can often lead to overwhelm. I think what Plath is trying to suggest is that the combination of ambition and a lack of direction can often lead to feelings of helplessness and anxiety. As a character who has worked relentlessly all of her life, Esther consequently suffers from having to choose between a number of ‘wonderful future[s]’ but is incapable of choosing just one ‘fig’. After some research, I discovered that ‘the green fig tree’ is possibly an allusion to a biblical story. In this story, Jesus and his disciples come across a fig tree that had many green leaves. However, upon drawing closer, the tree only had leaves and no fruit. Perhaps this suggests that, deep down, the character of Esther knows that none of these future possibilities will be fulfilled. Consequently, Esther’s fear of making the right decision overrides a fear of not making a decision at all, leaving her stranded and ‘starving to death’.</p>
<p>What I loved most about ‘The Bell Jar’ was Plath’s prose style. She uses rich figurative language and her writing is full of expertly crafted metaphors. This is ultimately what makes the novel engaging, sorrowful and cathartic. Although it is a difficult read, I was immersed in the world Plath creates and hence, I would give it five stars. Everyone should read this.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Classics</category>
            <category>Fiction</category>
            <category>Feminism</category>
            <category>Mental Health</category>
            <category>Psychology</category>
            <category>Poetry</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Catcher in the Rye, J.D Salinger]]></title>
            <link>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/catcher</link>
            <guid>https://laylamaywilliams.github.io/blog/catcher</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<img]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://abc.nl/covers/9780316769488/200" alt="Book Cover: The Catcher in the Rye" style="float:left;margin-right:20px;margin-bottom:10px;max-width:150px;height:auto">
<p>J.D Salinger's 'The Catcher in the Rye' covers a timeline of just over two days and follows the journey of a teenage boy, expelled from boarding school, as he makes his way home. Throughout the novella, we see his interactions with various characters, both the 'phonies' and those he loves. Whilst it is largely considered a modern classic, the mixed reviews came as a shock to me.</p>
<p>Many believe that the protagonist, Holden, is a selfish, spoilt malcontent and that the novella's language is limited. Personally, I would argue that the language in the novel is chosen carefully to enhance the character voice and give the reader a true insight to the mind of a troubled teen. As for Holden himself, whilst I'll admit he is not the most likeable, his hardships in life, such as losing his brother at just thirteen, should not be ignored. I think that people are often inadvertently dismissive of the character's that they do not immediately relate to or those that are flawed. However, this should not be a cause for coming to the conclusion that the novella is poorly written. I believe that Salinger carefully captures the imperfect workings of Holden's mind creating a slow, but ultimately heart-warming story.</p>
<p>Holden should be a sympathetic character. He alienates himself from his peers and views the majority of adults in his life as 'phony'. Whilst his attitude is evidently judgemental, arguably, it is the character's way of avoiding failure or emotional pain. Another way in which Salinger portrays Holden as a sympathetic is through his repetitive allusions to suicide. By writing these comments in a casual way, Salinger explores the fine line between teenage angst and serious depression. For me and likely many other readers, Holden's dissatisfaction with life is initially difficult to comprehend; he comes from a wealthy family, has a loving sister and has every opportunity within his reach. Yet, as the story proceeds, the depth of Holden's unhappiness becomes apparent as his emotions become evidently more troubling than those of the average adolescent. Maybe, it is not a matter of 'why' the character should feel this way, but rather a reflection of those emotions in general.</p>
<p>My favourite parts of his story are those depicted with his younger sister, Phoebe. It is because of his perceptive sister that Holden eventually begins to take responsibility for his life and actions towards the end of the novel. I also believe that these interactions remind us, as readers that, despite Holden's tough facade, he is still just a child. His misinterpretation of Robert Burns' 'Comin' Thro the Rye' perhaps acts as a metaphor for Holden's discomfort with growing up and reaching adulthood, further conveying his childish nature. I think it is interesting that Salinger chose to use this poem since its predominant theme is the question of whether or not casual sex is okay. One could interpret that this decision links to the protagonist's internal struggle surrounding sex and women.</p>
<p>As for those who think the novella is lacking in plot, I believe they are missing the point. It is not meant to be an action packed story. I would interpret that Salinger aimed to highlight the importance of both friends, family and strangers in shaping an individuals life. Each character Holden meets, even in this short period of time, influences the decisions he makes and eventually, as mentioned before, his decision to work out what he wants to do with his life. This idea actually made me think of 'Station Eleven' by Emily St. John Mandel when one of the characters reflects, moments before her death, on how different life would be if a single person, even a stranger, was not in it.</p>
<p>Overall, I would give this book three stars. Whilst there is depth to the novella and its protagonist, personally, it wasn't my favourite modern classic. I can see its literary value but I simply did not enjoy it enough to give it five stars. That being said, I would still encourage you to read it if you haven't already and to let me know what you thought!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>book review</category>
            <category>dystopian</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>